Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.17
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Ongoing Career, 1993; XVII.
  - Articles and Issues, 8.
    - New Material Added, December 2014
      - Articles about Thornburgh Accomplishments
        - Articles, 1998-2004 (Box 1045, Folder 41)
        - History of Attorney General policies (Thornburgh & others), 2004 (Box 1045, Folder 42)
        - Articles, 2005-2012 (Box 1045, Folder 43)
    - New Material Added, May 2017
      - Law Suits re: US Senate 1991 Campaign, 1992-1994
        Following Thornburgh's unsuccessful Campaign for US Senate in 1991 law suits were initiated by two creditors, Carl Rove and Optima Direct Inc., regarding campaign debts incurred close to election day for "get out the vote" efforts. Attempts to raise further funds at that time were hampered, among other things, by Thornburgh's almost immediate appointment to the United Nations, which prohibited political fund-raising. Ultimately the Thornburgh's were obliged to cover the shortfall with their own personal funds.
        - Appeal Correspondence Rove v. Thornburgh, July 1993-March 1994 (Box 1042, Folder 1)
        - Federal Election Commission Matters, September 1993-January 1994 (Box 1042, Folder 2)
        - Trial Correspondence Rove v. Thornburgh, March 1992-August 1993 (Box 1042, Folder 3)
        - Trial Pleadings, July 1992-September 1992 (Box 1042, Folder 4)
        - Trial Briefs (including drafts) and Opinions, April-June 1993 (Box 1042, Folder 5)
        - Trial: RLT Notes, March 1993-August 1993 (Box 1042, Folder 6)
        - Correspondence and documents, August-October 1993 (Box 1042, Folder 7)
        - Correspondence and documents, January-March 1994 (Box 1042, Folder 8)
        - Documents, August-September 1993 (Box 1042, Folder 9)
        - Thornburgh Telephone Deposition Transcript, September 17, 1993 (Box 1042, Folder 10)
        - Correspondence and documents, December 1993-March 1994 (Box 1042, Folder 11)
        - Pre-trial deposition: Richard Thornburgh, September 9, 1992 (Box 1042, Folder 12)
        - Pre-trial deposition: Murray Dickman, September 10, 1992 (Box 1042, Folder 13)
        - Pre-trial deposition: Raymond P. Dimuzio, November 11, 1992 (Box 1042, Folder 14)
        - Draft Brief & Motion: Dimuzio, March 13, 1994 (Box 1042, Folder 15)
        - Draft Brief: Thornburgh, March 1994 (Box 1042, Folder 16)
        - Amicus Curia drafts & final of RNC in support of Richard L. Thornburgh in Rove v. Thornburgh, December 1993 (Box 1042, Folder 17)
        - Optima settlement correspondence, August 1993-March 1994 (Box 1042, Folder 18)
        - Optima v. Thornburgh settlement/PMA Agreements, March 1994 (Box 1042, Folder 19)
        - RLT notes Optima Direct v. Thornburgh, 1993-1994 (Box 1042, Folder 20)
        - General correspondence, March - September 1993 (Box 1042, Folder 21)
        - Optima deposition: Murray Dickman, July 29, 1993 (Box 1042, Folder 22)
        - Optima deposition: Raymond Dimozio, May 5, 1993 (Box 1042, Folder 23)
        - Rove v. Thornburgh excerpt of testimony: Murray Dickman, April 2, 1993 (Box 1042, Folder 24)
        - Optima v. Thornburgh General Pleading & Pre-trial matters, 1993 (Box 1042, Folder 25)
  - "Where the Evidence Leads", 9.
    Thornburgh's autobiography was published by the University of Pittsburgh Press in 2004. This section includes the prepublication tours, articles about the book, interviews with Thornburgh, pre-publication notes and promotion activities July-August, 2003 and reviews 2003. (The first paperback edition was later printed in 2010.)
    - Thornburgh notes and outline pre-publication, 1993-1994 (Box 1038, Folder 21)
    - Attorney General "achievements and record", 1989-1991 (Box 1038, Folder 22)
    - Promotion plans: Jamie Moss, January-September 2003 (Box 1038, Folder 23)
    - Review lists, ad plans, May-September 2003 (Box 1038, Folder 24)
    - Book Reviews, November-December 2003 (Box 1038, Folder 25)
    - Interview: Marc Schogol, Philadelphia Inquirer, August 13, 2003 (Box 1038, Folder 26)
    - WHYY-PA Public Broadcasting Interview, September 15, 2003 (Box 1038, Folder 27)
    - Call-In with Matt Gerson, September 15, 2003 (Box 1038, Folder 28)
    - Interview: John Miller of Philadelphia Metro, September 15, 2003 (Box 1038, Folder 29)
    - Live taping: CBS Newsmakers Program, September 15, 2003 (Box 1038, Folder 30)
    - NOW Interview Century City Studio Philadelphia, September 16, 2003 (Box 1038, Folder 31)
    - PCN-PA Cable Network Interview re PA Books, September 16, 2003 (Box 1038, Folder 32)
    - Legal Intelligencer Interview, September 16, 2003 (Box 1038, Folder 33)
    - Book signing: Free Library of Philadelphia, September 16, 2003 (Box 1038, Folder 34)
    - American University Book Signing, October 2, 2003 (Box 1038, Folder 35)
    - Book and Author Dinner, Pittsburgh, November 6, 2003 (Box 1038, Folder 36)
    - National Press Club Book Fair, Washington, D.C., November 12, 2003 (Box 1038, Folder 37)
  - Varied Subjects of Interest, 10.
    These articles relate to varied subjects Thornburgh followed ongoing, for example: DOJ cases he handled when AG, crime issues, Pennsylvania issues re his Administration, Taiwan/China, assorted justice related issues (terrorism and homeland security for example), baseball, merit selection, Voter ID, and Supreme Court decision, Thornburgh Blogs and published essays, 2000 Presidential Election, Florida Supreme Court Case, Roberts Nomination to Supreme Court.
    - DOJ Case: Pilon v. DOJ, June 3, 1993 (Box 1040, Folder 1)
    - DOJ Case: Bassil v. Richard Thornburgh, October 4, 1993 (Box 1040, Folder 2)
    - DOJ Case: "MIT" case decision, September 2, 1992 (Box 1040, Folder 3)
    - DOJ Case: "VMI" case decision, October 5, 1992 (Box 1040, Folder 4)
    - DOJ Issue: Thornburgh Memorandum / McDade Bill, 1994-2001 (Box 1040, Folder 5)
    - DOJ Initiative: Operation Weed and Seed, Status, 2000 (Box 1040, Folder 6)
    - Crime articles, 1994 (Box 1040, Folder 7)
    - Crime articles, 1995 (Box 1040, Folder 8)
    - Crime articles, 1996 (Box 1040, Folder 9)
    - Pennsylvania: Ben Franklin Partnership Executive Summaries, 1989-2013 (Box 1040, Folder 10)
    - Pennsylvania: Governor Commutations and Life sentences compared, October 2005 (Box 1040, Folder 11)
    - Pennsylvania politics and issue comparisons: Gubernatorial election, 2010 (Box 1040, Folder 12)
    - "UN Should Welcome Taiwan," Far Eastern Economic Review, August 1993 (Box 1040, Folder 13)
    - Sigur Center: "The Election and Taiwan's Democratic Development", April 8-9, 1994 (Box 1040, Folder 14)
    - Sigur Center: "Cross-straits Relations: A View from Washington, April 8-9, 1994 (Box 1040, Folder 15)
    - Taiwan and arms sales, Spring 1994 (Box 1040, Folder 16)
    - Taiwan articles, May-June 1994 (Box 1040, Folder 17)
    - Taiwan- China issues and articles, 1994-2001 (Box 1040, Folder 18)
    - China: Human Rights Watch, Wei Jing Sueng, and Liu, 1995-1999 (Box 1040, Folder 19)
    - Rule of Law articles, 1993-2000 (Box 1040, Folder 20)
    - War on Terror, articles, 2002-2003 (Box 1040, Folder 21)
    - Terrorists, Criminal or Military Justice?, October 2001-2006 (Box 1040, Folder 22)
    - Book: Homeland Security and American Politics, Thornburgh forward, 2004 (Box 1040, Folder 23)
    - Terrorist Surveillance and the Constitution issues, 2007-2008 (Box 1040, Folder 24)
    - Homeland Security and Rule of Law issues, 2009 (Box 1040, Folder 25)
    - Baseball: Forward by Thornburgh "Bring Back Judge Landis!" for "Judge & Jury: the Life and Times of Judge Kenesaw Mountain Landis,", October 2001 (Box 1040, Folder 26)
    - Baseball articles and notes, 2001-2006 (Box 1040, Folder 27)
    - Baseball articles by John Updike and others, 1960-2005 (Box 1040, Folder 28)
    - Re: "Bucky Walters" & efforts to get him into Baseball Hall of Fame, 1999-2008 (Box 1040, Folder 29)
    - "Bucky Walters" portfolio of materials and correspondence re his career, 2005 (Box 1040, Folder 30)
    - Merit selection backed by Governors, 2013 (Box 1040, Folder 31)
    - Voter ID, draft op-ed and articles, PA court opinion, 2012 (Box 1040, Folder 32)
    - Affordable Care Act Supreme Court Opinion, annotated, June 28, 2012 (Box 1040, Folder 33)
    - Blog: "Needed: Real-World Experience," (Justice Stephens retirement), New York Times, April 28, 2012 (Box 1040, Folder 34)
    - Blog: "The Wild Card Factor" re Supreme Court appointment of Elena Kagan, New York Times, May 10, 2010 (Box 1040, Folder 35)
    - Essay: "Attorney General: Don't Try to Be Loved," Newsweek, November 4, 2008 (Box 1040, Folder 36)
    - Essay: "Memo to the next Attorney General," National Journal, December 11, 2008 (Box 1040, Folder 37)
    - Presidential Election 2000, Florida ballot issue, November 9-13, 2000 (Box 1040, Folder 38)
    - Presidential Election 2000, Maps, November 9, 2000 (Box 1040, Folder 39)
    - Presidential Election 2000, Manual recounts, November 15-18, 2000 (Box 1040, Folder 40)
    - Presidential Election 2000, Florida Legislature role, November 22, 2000 (Box 1040, Folder 41)
    - Presidential Election 2000, Supreme Court to hear case, November 24-28, 2000 (Box 1040, Folder 42)
    - Presidential Election 2000, Bush - Gore Positions, November 27-30 (Box 1040, Folder 43)
    - Presidential Election 2000, Talk Show talking points, December 2, 2000 (Box 1040, Folder 44)
    - Presidential Election 2000, Supreme Court Arguments, December 11-14, 2000 (Box 1040, Folder 45)
    - Roberts Nomination 2005, To US Court of Appeals, December 18, 2002 (Box 1040, Folder 46)
    - Roberts Nomination 2005, Roberts' Record, July 11-20, 2005 (Box 1040, Folder 47)
    - Roberts Nomination 2005, Reactions to Nomination, July 22-28, 2005 (Box 1040, Folder 48)
    - Roberts Nomination 2005, Opinions re Nomination, August 25-28, 2005 (Box 1040, Folder 49)
    - Roberts Nomination 2005, Opinions re Nomination, August 29-31, 2005 (Box 1040, Folder 50)
    - Roberts Nomination 2005, Letters of support and hearing, September 1-12, 2005 (Box 1040, Folder 51)
  - Three Mile Island, 11.
    - "Minutes to Meltdown- How America fame close to a nuclear Catastrophe," NBC News, August 16, 2001 (Box 1040, Folder 52)
    - "Status and Future of Nuclear Power in US," by Larry Foulke, American Nuclear Society Symposium, October 16, 2002 (Box 1040, Folder 53)
    - "Commonwealth of PA, Office of Governor" Report re TMI, April 2, 2003 (Box 1040, Folder 54)
    - Articles Re Swanson School Nuclear Engineering Program, 2008 (Box 1040, Folder 55)
    - Extensive articles re TMI 30th "anniversary", March 2009 (Box 1040, Folder 56)
    - Thornburgh speech "Mitigating Consequences of Complex Systems Failures" and articles, 2009-2010 (Box 1040, Folder 57)
    - Dr. Vagel Keller documents and article for a TMI case study, 2009-2010 (Box 1040, Folder 58)
    - Dr. Keller's Thornburgh Interview Transcript and Final Paper, 2011 (Box 1040, Folder 59)
    - Articles re Japan nuclear catastrophe relating to TMI, March 2011 (Box 1040, Folder 60)
  - Awards and Honors, 12.
    Dick Thornburgh, Ginny Thornburgh, separately and together have received many distinguished awards for their notable accomplishments related to disabilities and numerous other subjects for Dick Thornburgh particularly. These events and related articles reflect the esteem recognized by many individuals and organizations.
    - Thornburgh elected to membership, American Law Institute, May 18, 2000 (Box 1039, Folder 77)
    - Mercersburg Academy "diploma" on fiftieth anniversary of Class of 1950, to Richard L. Thornburgh in token of devotion to the ideals of his school, October 21, 2000 (Box 1039, Folder 78)
    - Severin Fayerman Patriot Award to Dick and Ginny Thornburgh, Berks County GOP, October 29, 2001 (Box 1039, Folder 79)
    - Bikur Cholin Hospital's International Brotherhood Award to Dick Thornburgh and Ginny Thornburgh in recognition of their outstanding contributions to their communities and professions, Capital Hilton, March 12, 2002 (Box 1039, Folder 80)
    - Correspondence and related background to Bikur Cholin Hospital Honor (Box 1039, Folder 81)
    - ASME (American Society of Mechanical Engineers) Award, Public Affairs Leadership Conference, Alexandria, VA, May 6, 2002 (Box 1039, Folder 82)
    - Wiley Branton Award for Civil Rights to Dick Thornburgh for his outstanding work on behalf of disability rights, by Washington Lawyers Committee for Civil Rights, June 5, 2002 (Box 1039, Folder 83)
    - Lincoln Day 2003 honoring Dick Thornburgh on the 140th Anniversary of the Union League, and 194th Anniversary of Lincoln's birth, Philadelphia, February 12, 2003 (Box 1039, Folder 84)
    - AAPD Betts Award to Dick and Ginny Thornburgh in recognition of their work to improve quality of life for all people with disabilities, Washington, March 4, 2003 (Box 1039, Folder 85)
    - Achiever's Circle Luncheon Honoring Dick and Ginny Thornburgh, 2003 Bette Award for outstanding service to people with disabilities, June 19, 2003 (Box 1039, Folder 86)
    - American Tort Reform Association (ATRA)named Dick Thornburgh in its first-ever group of "Legal Reform Champions", Washington, July 3, 2003 (Box 1039, Folder 87)
    - Lifetime Service Award, Federalist Society for Law and Public Policy, Georgetown University, February 18, 2004 (Box 1039, Folder 88)
    - Millersville 150th Anniversary Medallion of Honor, for public service and role in signing 1983 law creating State System of Higher Education, September 9, 2004 (Box 1039, Folder 89)
    - Community Resources for Independent Living (SRI), Independent Living Legacy Award to Governor Dick and Ginny Thornburgh Award, May 22, 2004 (Box 1039, Folder 90)
    - Pittsburgh Council for International Visitors '05 Bridge Award recognizing his promoting Pittsburgh and the US throughout the world, Pittsburgh, April 23, 2005 (Box 1039, Folder 91)
    - Jewish Foundation for Group Homes, Robert Cohen Award to Dick and Ginny Thornburgh for their support on behalf of people with disabilities, October 27, 2005 (Box 1039, Folder 92)
    - Disability Rights Legal Center Award to Richard & Virginia Thornburgh and son Peter, Los Angeles, November 17, 2005 (Box 1039, Folder 93)
    - 2006 American Lawyer Lifetime Achiever Award, New York, October 25, 2006 (Box 1039, Folder 94)
    - Personal Congratulations from PA Governor Rendell to Governor Thornburgh as he received the American Lawyers' Lifetime Achievement Award, October 25, 2006 (Box 1039, Folder 95)
    - "Best Lawyers in America, 2008 25th Anniversary Edition" (and succeeding years), 2007-2011 (Box 1045, Folder 33)
    - Dick Thornburgh, Trustee Emeritus, University of Pittsburgh, October 31, 2008 (Box 1045, Folder 34)
    - Senate of Pennsylvania Special Recognition to Dick Thornburgh, 2008 Speaker Franklin Award, Pittsburgh, November 11, 2008 (Box 1045, Folder 35)
    - Honorary Doctor of Laws Degree, from Bethany College, September 11, 2009 (Box 1045, Folder 36)
    - United Spinal Association awards Dick and Ginny Thornburgh: 2010 Visionary Award, Tireless Advocates for People with disabilities and commemorating 20th Anniversary of ADA, Philadelphia, May 1, 2010 (Box 1045, Folder 37)
    - Edna Silberman Humanitarian Award: Dick and Ginny Thornburgh, November 3, 2011 (Box 1045, Folder 38)
    - Neighborhood Legal Tribute, May 16, 2011 (Box 1045, Folder 39)
    - Pitt Law Magazine, "Leaving a Legacy", Fall 2012 (Box 1045, Folder 40)